Mohammad Merajul Islam Molla

Email: meraj.enigma@gmail.com • Mobile: + (880) 177-682402 • Skype: mmm2177

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/merajenigma • Github://imeraj

Plot-77, Block-C, Apt-A3, Banani, Dhaka, 1213, Bangladesh

Summary

About 10 years of industry and academic experience working with diverse technologies ranging from low-level system software to mobile/web applications, project management, company strategy and policy making, along with new business development and introducing new technologies to meet dynamic nature of tech industry.

Have experience working in multiple countries - USA, Japan, India, South Korea and with clients from different countries - USA, South Korea, Japan, and Australia. Good verbal and written communication skills and comfortable working with colleagues and clients from diverse culture.

INTERESTS: New Technology R&D, Software Architecture, Project Management, Mobile Application Development, Server-side Programming, Software Quality Assurance, Embedded Systems, Recruitment & Team Building

Experience

CTO (Mobile Technology), Monstar Lab Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD

Jan 2017 - Oct 2017

- Supervised Mobile (iOS, Android), Infrastructure, and QA Teams
- Supervised projects: Earthcar (http://www.earthcar.co.jp) Taxi app (Android) Uber like taxi booking app. R&D for iOS app.
- Conducted regular trainings, tech talks, and internal tech sessions for high performance team building
- Highly involved in recruitment, project estimation, employee evaluation, and company strategy determination

Senior Architect (Mobile Technology), Monstar Lab Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD

May 2016 - Dec 2016

- Built and supervised Mobile (iOS, Android) teams from scratch
- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for mobile projects (iOS, Android)
- Supervised projects: A2MILKBAR departmental store management app (iOS, Android, PHP/Node.js), Askul (http://www.askul.co.jp) E-commerce App (iOS, Android)

Chief Engineer (Mobile SW), Samsung R&D Institute Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD Mar 2014 - May 2016

- Worked as Tech Lead of Samsung Gear S and Gear Fit Manager applications and managed 20+ team members
- Supervised multiple internal projects for iOS, Android and Tizen platforms Log Analyzer, Emergency Service, TizenFlip, Samsung Guardian App, etc
- Managed small team of 3 members to contribution to open source project Linaro

Lead Engineer (Mobile SW), Samsung R&D Institute Bangladesh, Dhaka, BD May 2012 - Mar 2014

- Worked as Team Lead of Call and Driver Teams of Feature Phone Mobile Commercilisation division and managed around 10+ team members
- Worked as Tech Lead of Qshare (Quick Share) project on Android platform

System SW Engineer (MAC OS Graphics Driver Team, NVIDIA, CA, USA

Jan 2008 - Aug 2011

- Worked on various components of Display Drivers and core RM Software (Hotplug Architecture, Display Port, Mobile PCI Express Module (MXM), Interrupt Handling, DVI Port, HDCP Protocol, VBIOS, etc).
- Implemented in C and x86 assembly

MTS Intern (CPD, VMware ESX Server Team), VMware, CA, USA

May 2007 - Aug 2007

- Developed Kernel Crash Dump tool for VMware ESX Server.
- Implemented in C and bash script

MTS Intern (CPD, VMware ESX Server Team), VMware Inc, CA, USA

May 2006 - Aug 2006

- Developed Filesystem Debugger for VMware ESX Server.
- Implemented in C and bash script

Education

Marquette University, MS in Computing

Dec 2007

- CGPA: 4.00/4.00
- Final Project: Implementation of device driver for Broadcom?s BCM4713 Ethernet card on Linksys WRT54GL router and integrating it with Xinu Kernel

BUET, BS in CSE Nov 2004

- CGPA: 3.92/4.00
- Thesis: Study of Various Popular Network Simulators and Case Studies using NS-2, Commonly Used Open Source Network Research Simulator, to Simulate Wired and Wireless Networks

Technical Skills

Programming Languages: Swift • Java • Kotlin • Ruby • Elixir • Objective-C • C • C++ Assembly(x86, MIPS)

Mobile Platforms: iOS • Android

Mobile Architecture Patterns: MVC • MVP • VIP • RxVIP

Mobile Frameworks/Tools: RxSwift • RxJava • Alamofire • Retrofit 2 • Gilde • Picasso • Alamofire • Retrofit 2 • Gilde • Picasso • Alamofire • Retrofit 2 • Gilde • Picasso • Alamofire • RxJava • Alam

Web Frameworks: Phoenix • Ruby on Rails • Vapor

Quality Assurance: Cucumber • Calabash • XCTest • ExUnit • MiniTest

Infrastructure: Docker • Nanobox • Heroku

Database: Mysql • Sqlite • Realm • MongoDB • Redis

Project Management: JIRA • Redmine • Trello **Version Control:** Git • Perforce • Subversion

Real-time Services: Pusher • PubNub

Miscelleneous: GraphQL • Protobuf • Blockchain

Professional Projects

Earthcar Taxi App (iOS, Android)

2017 (Ongoing)

Uber like Taxi app for Earthcar (http://www.earthcar.co.jp) Japan. Three different applications - User App (Android, Smartphone), User App (iOS, Smartphone) and Driver App (Android, Tab) along with backend APIs/services and front-end Admin panel.

- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for mobile apps
- Conducted R&D, designed app architecture, and guided engineers to implement features
- Derived project estimation from client requirements, broke down features into sprints, worked with QA Engineers to define test specifications
- Conducted code review and managed branch/release policies
- Collaborated with backend engineers for smooth integration of APIs/services with mobile apps

Askul E-commerce App (iOS, Android)

2017

E-commerce applications developed for Askul (http://www.askul.co.jp) Japan. Two different applications - one for iOS and another for Android

- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for the project
- Conducted R&D, designed app architecture, and guided developers to implement features
- Conducted code review and managed branch/release policies
- Backend APIs/services developed using Java (Spring Boot) by 3rd party in Japan
- Conducted regular meeting and status reporting with Japan side project stakeholders

A2MILKBAR App (iOS, Android)

2016

Departmental store management app developed for Australian client. Two different applications - one for iOS and another for Android platform along with backend APIs/services and front-end Admin panel.

- Worked as Tech Lead and Project Manager for the project
- Conducted R&D, designed app architecture, and guided developers to implement features
- Conducted code review and managed branch/release policies
- Backend APIs/services developed using PHP and Node.js

Samsung Gear S and Samsung Gear Fit Apps (iOS)

2015-2016

Developed commercial versions of Samsung Gear S and Gear Fit Apps to work with Tizen powered Gear S2 and Gear Fit 2.

- Developed in collaboration with Samsung HQ (South Korea)
- Conducted R&D, designed and developed Basic Accessory Protocol (BAP) on top of Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE). The protocol supports - file transfer with pause/resume/cancel, CRC and retransmission, QoS
- Designed and developed Webproxy module to support multiple Gear apps, such as Weather, S-Voice, Voice Memo, etc
- Notifications using Apple Notification Center Service, along with notification settings, block notifications
- Samsung Gear S https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/samsung-gear-s/id1117310635?mt=8
- Samsung Gear Fit https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/samsung-gear-fit/id1117312500?mt=8

Academic Projects

Porting (Xinu) Operating System on Linksys WRT54GL Router

2006-2007

The purpose of the project is to port Xinu OS, developed at Purdue University, on a modified version of Linksys WRT54GL router. Linksys WRT54GL has BCM947XX chipset with MIPS processor (Broadcom's BCM3302) and comes with OpenWrt Linux distribution.

- Cisco & Intel Funded
- Implemented exception and interrupt handler for the chipset and integrated it with Xinu
- Programmed timer interrupt and integrated it with Xinu's context switch code to enable kernel pre-emption and support process scheduling
- Implemented lower-half of interrupt driven asynchronous serial driver (UART 16550) for the router platform
- Implemented Ethernet device driver for Broadcom's BCM4713 card on this platform
- Implemented in C and MIPS assembly programming languages
- Github link https://github.com/xinu-os/xinu

Integrating Speex Codec in Columbia InterNet Extensible Multimedia Architecture (CINEMA) 2005 CINEMA is a set of SIP-based Internet Multimedia Servers for creating an Enterprise Telephony and

Multimedia system. CINEMA consists of sipd (SIP redirect, proxy, and registrar server), sipconf (SIP Audio Conference Server), sipum (SIP/RTSP unified messaging system), sip323 (SIP-H.323 signaling gateway), rtspd (RTSP streaming media server).

- Integrated open source speex codec in sipconf conferencing server of CINEMA
- Supported two modes of speex codec narrow-band (8KHz sampling rate) and wide-band (16KHz sampling rate)
- Fixed several bugs in existing conference server to make the codec work properly within CINEMA architecture
- Tested integration of speex codec using Linphone
- Implemented in C++ programming language

Open Source Contribution

Linaro Project - http://www.linaro.org

2015

Led a team of 3 engineers for making contribution to Open Source project (Linaro) - open source software for ARM SoCs and made decent contribution to their power management tools - powertop, powerdebug, idlestat, and pm-qa.

Achievement/Awards

- 2017 Ranked 2nd in Monstar Lab ISUCON Tech Olympics (Web App Performance Tuning contest)
- 2017 Promoted as CTO of Mobile Technology Division
- 2015 Won Employee of the Year Award (SRBD)
- 2015 Won Iconic Team award for iOS Gear Manager Team for 2H of Y2015 (SRBD)

Nominated as Employee of the Year (SRBD)
Iconic Team award for Android Development Team for 2H of Y2014 (SRBD)
Achived Double promotion (promoted from Lead Engineer to Chief Engineer, SRBD)
Won Graduate Assistantship (Marquette University)
Won Dean's List Award (BUET)
Won University Merit Scholarship (BUET)
Won Board Merit Scholarship (Bangladesh Government)

Hobbies

Reading novels, music, movies, travelling